<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Bevis of Hampton]</title>
            <title>Beuve de Hanstone.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1500</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1987</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111740</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847017</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847017</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12020</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09589)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12020)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 72:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Bevis of Hampton]</title>
                  <title>Beuve de Hanstone.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. de Worde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Westminster :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1500]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Based on the twelfth-century Anglo-Norman chanson de geste "Beuve de Hanstone".</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Thirty-two lines to a page; 95 mm. textura with capital "T" having crooked stem. Begins on leaf 2 recto; line 1 there reads: In all the londes of crystyente--STC.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; a fragment of two leaves.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:12020:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:12020:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 22 -->
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <l>In all the londes of cryſtyenie</l>
            <l>Was none founde ſo good as he</l>
            <l>Whyle he was younge and Iolyfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>Wolde ſyr Guy wedde no wyfe.</l>
            <l>But whan he began to elde</l>
            <l>Wexed feble and vnwelde</l>
            <l>And toke his leue of cheualry</l>
            <l>And dwelled in Englonde certaynly</l>
            <l>In that tyme kynge Edgar anone.</l>
            <l>Sente after ſyr Guy full ſone.</l>
            <l>And ſyt Guy was true and wyce.</l>
            <l>And knowen for a knyght of pryce</l>
            <l>He made hym hyghe ſtewarde of his londe.</l>
            <l>And what ſo euer he ſayd it ſholde ſtonde.</l>
            <l>He kepte well Englonde in his dayes</l>
            <l>And ſet peas and ſtable layes</l>
            <l>That no man was ſo hardy</l>
            <l>To do another velany.</l>
            <l>Vpon a daye thought ſyr Guy</l>
            <l>That he wolde wedde ſome fayre lady</l>
            <l>And haue bytwene them ſome chyldren fayre.</l>
            <l>That of theyr londe myght be theyr heyre.</l>
            <l>The kynge of Scotlonde in that tyde.</l>
            <l>Had a doughter of grete pryde.</l>
            <l>The emperours broder of Almayne</l>
            <l>Loued <gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lady, as men ſayne</l>
            <l>But Guy wedded her god hym ſaue</l>
            <l>And at her fader he dyd her craue</l>
            <l>The kynge of ſcotlonde not for thy</l>
            <l>Gaue his doughter vnto ſyr Guy</l>
            <l>Ayenſt the wyll of his doughter bryght</l>
            <l>She had leuer haue hadde the other knyght.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12020:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
For he was yonge and bolde.</l>
            <l>And ſyr Guy was wexen olde</l>
            <l>Alas that euer he her to hym choſe</l>
            <l>His owne lyfe for her to loſe.</l>
            <l>Syr Guy wedded that lady free.</l>
            <l>And brought her home to his countree</l>
            <l>So longe to bedde he her ledde.</l>
            <l>That a man chylde to gyder they hadde.</l>
            <l>Beuys they called that childe bolde.</l>
            <l>He was no more but ſeuyn yere olde.</l>
            <l>Whan his fader was ſlayne</l>
            <l>With ſyr Mordure of almayne</l>
            <l>That lady betought her vpon a daye<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>And vnto her ſelfe ganne ſhe ſaye</l>
            <l>My lorde is olde and maye not wyrche</l>
            <l>Alle daye he goth vnto the chyrche</l>
            <l>What for breyſynge and what for age.</l>
            <l>He louech not with me for to rage</l>
            <l>But hadde I take a yonge knyght.</l>
            <l>That hadde not ben bruſyd in fyght.</l>
            <l>He wolde me loue both daye and nyght.</l>
            <l>And make me all the myrth that he myght</l>
            <l>Truly it ſhall be thus noo whyle.</l>
            <l>I ſhall let ſle hym wyth ſumme gyle</l>
            <l>After a meſſenger the lady ſende.</l>
            <l>That before he was her frende</l>
            <l>And ſayd thou ſhalt on my meſſage.</l>
            <l>Thy ſelfe alone without ony page</l>
            <l>With that thou holde it counceyll.</l>
            <l>I ſhall the quyte for thy trauayll</l>
            <l>Madame he ſayd holde you ſtyll:</l>
            <l>For I wyll do all at your wyll.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12020:2"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 23 -->
My lorde the it ſente ſyr mordure.</l>
            <l>To nyght he commyth to thy bourt</l>
            <l>This yet tel he ſayde is lefe to me.</l>
            <l>And tanke ſyr mordure of his gentre.</l>
            <l>And ſaye I am all at his wyll.</l>
            <l>Erly and late londe and ſtyll.</l>
            <l>The meſſenger away thenne wente</l>
            <l>And tolde his lorde as ſhe had ſent</l>
            <l>NOwe wyll we of yonge Beuys tell</l>
            <l>Howe woo he was and howe hym be felle.</l>
            <l>Alas he ſayd all for tene.</l>
            <l>That I had not wyth my fader been</l>
            <l>To haue holpyn my fader in that ſtome</l>
            <l>Ayenſt that falſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heef ſyr mordure</l>
            <l>To his moder he ran and ſayde.</l>
            <l>Why haſte thou my fader betrayed:</l>
            <l>I wyll be wrokyn of his bane.</l>
            <l>Alas that euer thou were womane</l>
            <l>And all falſe hores for thy ſake</l>
            <l>To the denyll of hell I them betake.</l>
            <l>But one othe moder I the ſwere</l>
            <l>yf I may euer armes bere</l>
            <l>I ſhall be venged wyth myght and mayne</l>
            <l>On them that hathe my fader ſlayne</l>
            <l>His moder his wordes vnderſtode.</l>
            <l>And gaue hym a buffet vpon the hode.</l>
            <l>To the grou<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e he fell and that was harme</l>
            <l>His mayſter toke hym vp by the arme</l>
            <l>Men called his mayſter ſyr Sabere</l>
            <l>That chylde was to hym left and dere</l>
            <l>For Sabere was ſyr Guyes broder.</l>
            <l>In Englonde was not ſuche an other.</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:12020:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 24 -->
Home withe th chylde he wente.</l>
            <l>The lady after Sabyre ſente.</l>
            <l>Sabyre ſhe ſayd for wele or for wo.</l>
            <l>My ſone beuye loke that thou ſlo</l>
            <l>For ſhall I neuer gladde be</l>
            <l>That daye that I hym ſee.</l>
            <l>Syr Sabyre was not well apayde</l>
            <l>But graunted as the lady ſayde.</l>
            <l>Home he wente full ſory in this wyſe.</l>
            <l>He toke for wyles and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lewe a gryce</l>
            <l>The ryche chyldes clothes fayre and good.</l>
            <l>He them beſpronge with the blode</l>
            <l>Syr Sabere all for drede</l>
            <l>Liothed the chylde in poore wede</l>
            <l>And ſayd beuys it behoueth the to kepe</l>
            <l>Vpon the felde all my ſhepe</l>
            <l>Tyll the ſpouſage be brought to an ende</l>
            <l>And then wyll we vnto wales wende.</l>
            <l>There is an erle ſybbe vnto the</l>
            <l>Thou ſhalte there dwelle and with hym be</l>
            <l>Whan thou arte wexen and armes may bere</l>
            <l>And haue ſtrenght harneys to were</l>
            <l>Than thou ſhalte clayme thyn herytage.</l>
            <l>And venge thy fader be thou of aege</l>
            <l>And I ſhall helpe the than to fyght</l>
            <l>With dynte of ſwerde to wynne thy ryght</l>
            <l>Therfore my ſhepe forth thou dryne</l>
            <l>That no man knowe thou be on lyue.</l>
            <l>And forth he wente with Sabyres ſhepe</l>
            <l>To the felde and ſore gan wepe.</l>
            <l>Whan beuys was on hygh vpon the downe.</l>
            <l>He loked to warde ſouth hampton</l>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:12020:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 26 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
